<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in St. Maries Church in Oxford, March xxiv. MDCX. at the solemnizing of the happy inauguration of our gracious soveraigne King Iames Wherein is proved that kings doe hold their kingdomes immediately from God. By Sebastian Benefield D. of Divinitie, Fellow of Corpus Christi College.</title>
            <author>Benefield, Sebastian, 1559-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1870</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115273</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850492</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850492</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08377)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15700)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 654:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in St. Maries Church in Oxford, March xxiv. MDCX. at the solemnizing of the happy inauguration of our gracious soveraigne King Iames Wherein is proved that kings doe hold their kingdomes immediately from God. By Sebastian Benefield D. of Divinitie, Fellow of Corpus Christi College.</title>
                  <author>Benefield, Sebastian, 1559-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15700:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15700:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> MARIES Church in Oxford, March xxiv. MDCX. at the ſolemnizing of the happy <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auguration of our gracious ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne</hi> KING IAMES.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS PROVED THAT KINGS DOE hold their kingdomes immediately from God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> SEBASTIAN BENEFIELD D. of Divinitie <hi>Fellow of Corpus Chriſti College.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Oxford,</hi> Printed by Joſeph Barnes. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15700:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15700:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, IOHN, BY THE DIVINE PROVIDENCE, <hi>LORD BISHOP OF LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Ing <hi>Salomon,</hi> one of wiſdomes offſpring, <hi>(Right Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>All rivers goe into the Sea.</hi> Some thinke they doe it to doe their <hi>homage,</hi> and pay <hi>tribute</hi> to that place, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they receiued their beginning. May this little <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> imitate thoſe rivers, it is all it careth for. It had beginning from your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> when the fourth time you worthily bore the higheſt office in our Vniverſitie. For your requeſt (even then a commaund to me) gaue it being. It now returns as <hi>homager</hi> and <hi>tributarie</hi> to your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and is glad that it ſeeth the light through your favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble countenance. God almightie enlarge his graces vpon your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and fill you with his
<pb facs="tcp:15700:3"/> ſtrength, that the Church of Chriſt here long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying you, may reioice to ſee the pride of many her enimies through you abated. <hi>From my ſtudy in Corpus Chriſti College. Septemb.</hi> 9. 1611.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips, in all duty and ſervice to be commaunded, <hi>SEBASTIAN BENEFIELD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15700:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 21. Ver. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thou hast ſet him as bleſsings for ever.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> King takes vpon him his Subiects perſon, to ſing an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a victoriall ſong, a gratulatorie ſong, a ſong of thankeſgiving for the manifold bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings derived from heaven by the King vpon the Subiect. This King was <hi>David:</hi> his Subiects <hi>the people of Iſraell:</hi> his Song <hi>this Pſalme:</hi> the Bleſſings <hi>perpetuall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iob,</hi> for his ſeaven ſonnes, when their feaſting daies were, did early<note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 1.5.</note> every day offer ſeaven Holocauſtes, ſo many burnt offerings; for he thought, <hi>It may be, that my ſonnes haue ſinned, and blaſphemed God in their hearts:</hi> and might not <hi>David</hi> for his ſubiects offer vp his ſacrifices,<note n="b" place="margin">Hoſ. 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>vitulos labiorum,</hi> the ſacrifices of praiſe &amp; thankeſgiving vpon the like thought? <hi>It may be that my people haue ſinned through their vnthankfulneſſe againſt God.</hi> God through my governement hath plentifully powred vpon my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple his bleſſings: it may be, that now waxen fat, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard him not to giue him thankes; therefore will I for them offer vnto him the ſacrifice of praiſe.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Sacrifice</hi> was this <hi>Pſalme.</hi> A pſalme to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not only of the <hi>civill Magiſtrate,</hi> as ſome affirme; nor only of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as others; but of the <hi>civill Magiſtrate,</hi> with reference to <hi>Chriſt. David</hi> was a type of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15700:4"/> 
               <hi>his kingdome</hi> of <hi>Chriſts kingdome;</hi> his victories were but <hi>Praeludia,</hi> as preambles or fore-runners of Chriſts victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Therefore ſpeaking of <hi>David,</hi> wee muſt ever haue an eie to Chriſt. And, as this people here acknowledgeth for their <hi>temporall eſtate,</hi> that the ſafetie of their king, was their ſafetie, and common ioy; ſo muſt it be acknowledged by vs, that vpon the victories of our head <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, dependeth our <hi>ſpirituall wellfare.</hi> Chriſts victories over ſinne, death, and hell, are our victories, and haue freed vs from the curſe of the Law; his reſurrection is a cauſe of ours; his exaltation is our ioy.</p>
            <p>This Pſalme thus vnderſtood (of <hi>David</hi> with reference to Chriſt, yet primarilie of <hi>David</hi>) hath 2. general partes. One is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an <hi>Enumeration</hi> of thoſe many bleſſings, wherewith God had bleſſed <hi>David;</hi> and this part is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for the firſt ſeaven verſes.</p>
            <p>The other is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; a <hi>confeſsion,</hi> or <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of the power of God, whereby he diſſipateth, and bringeth to naught the counſells of the wicked. Let the wicked aſſiſted with all the powers of hell, band themſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to doe harme to the Lordes annointed; they ſhall find that there is a God,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 144.10.</note> 
               <hi>Qui dat ſalutem regibus, That gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth deliverance vnto kings, and reſcueth David his ſervant from the hurtfull and cruell ſword.</hi> The right hand of the Lord ſhall find them out, and make them like a fierie oven in the time of his anger. This confeſſion of <hi>Davids</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple beginning at the eighth verſe, is concluded with an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphoneme in the 13. <hi>Be thou exalted, O Lord in thy ſtrength,</hi> ſo will we ſing and praiſe thy power.</p>
            <p>Returne we to the <hi>Enumeration</hi> of the bleſſings where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God had bleſſed <hi>David;</hi> and wee ſhall behold the king<note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 33.23</note> 
               <hi>filled with bleſsings</hi> from the Lord. He was filled with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15700:4"/> ioy of heart for the <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>ſalvation</hi> of God, <hi>verſ. 1.</hi> Whatſoever his <hi>heart</hi> could wiſh, or <hi>lippes</hi> requeſt, that was graunted him, <hi>v.</hi> 2. Hee was prevented with <hi>liberall bleſsings, v. 3.</hi> A <hi>crowne of pure Gold</hi> was ſet vpon his head, <hi>v. eod. Life</hi> was given him, a long life, <hi>v. 4. Glory, dignitie,</hi> &amp; <hi>honour</hi> in deſpite of his foes, were heaped on him, <hi>v. 5.</hi> Hee was appointed <hi>for bleſsings</hi> vnto his people, <hi>v. 6.</hi> and was <hi>made glad with the ioy of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance</hi> of the Lord, <hi>eod.</hi> And why was <hi>David</hi> thus filled with bleſſings from the Lord? Was it for any merit of his own? No. The 7 verſe will tell vs why it was. It was for the ſure truſt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence he had in God and his mercies. <hi>Becauſe the king truſteth in the Lord, and in the mercie of the moſt high, he ſhall not ſlide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of this abundance of bleſſings, firſt ſetled vpon K. <hi>Davids</hi> head, &amp; thence like <hi>Aarons</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 133.2.</note> 
               <hi>ointment</hi> deſcending, and ſending forth ſweet odoures of peace and proſperitie to the loweſt of his people, much might be brought to fit <hi>this daies</hi> Solemnitie. <hi>This day</hi> hath God given vs oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of meeting now the eighth time to celebrate it, to the glory of his holy name, to the honour of our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraigne, and to the comfort of his loiall ſubiects. To which purpoſe out of <hi>Davids</hi> ſtore of bleſſings, I haue made choiſe of that which is in the former part of the ſixt verſe, <hi>Thou haſt ſet him as bleſsings for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words you may call <hi>Davids exaltation.</hi> I obſerue in them 4. Circumſtances. The 1. is the <hi>authour</hi> of this <hi>exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; God.</hi> The 2. the <hi>exaltation</hi> it ſelfe; <hi>David</hi> appointed king over Iſraell. The 3. the <hi>ende</hi> of the exaltation; <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings</hi> to his people. The 4. the <hi>continuance</hi> of the bleſſings; <hi>For ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt ſet him as bleſsings for ever.] Thou;</hi> there is the authour. <hi>Haſt ſet him;</hi> there is the exaltation. <hi>As bleſsings;</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15700:5"/> there is the ende. <hi>For ever;</hi> there is the continuance.</p>
            <p>I will with all the ſpeede I may, paſſe through theſe circumſtances, that I may ſpeake ſomewhat to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall doctrine iſſuing hence; namely, that <hi>kings hold their kingdomes immediately from God.</hi> Whereof when I ſhall haue made ſome vſe, it wilbe time to conclude. Till then I commend my ſelfe to God his gracious aſſiſtance, and your Chriſtian patience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt ſet him as bleſsings for ever.</hi> The firſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is the <hi>autor</hi> of <hi>Davids exaltation.</hi> The autor is <hi>God</hi> called in the firſt verſe of this Pſalme by his honourableſt title, <hi>Iehovah,</hi> God! <hi>Excedit ſupereminentia divinitatis vſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati eloquij facultatem,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin de Trinitate, lib. 7. ca. 4.</hi> The ſupereminency of the Deity paſſeth mans vtterance; and therfore it is immediatly added, <hi>Meliùs cogitatur quàm dicitur;</hi> we can better thinke then ſpeake of God. Yet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we conſult with our deepeſt thoughts, we come ſhort of apprehending that <hi>incomprehenſible Maieſtie.</hi> That of S.<note n="f" place="margin">Lib. de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris &amp; filij u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate, <hi>if that booke be S. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hilarie</hi> is as true as vulgar, <hi>Certè hoc eſt Deus, quod &amp; cum dicitur, non poteſt dici; cum aeſtimatur, non poteſt aeſtimari; cum comparatur, non poteſt comparari; cum definitur, ipſe ſuâ defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitione creſcit.</hi> Out of doubt, whoſoever ſhall goe about to ſearch into the ſecrets and eſſence of the will of God,<note n="g" place="margin">Prov. 25.28.</note> 
               <hi>opprimetur à gloriâ,</hi> and feare and ſhame ſhalbe his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering.</p>
            <p>To ſuch curious ſearchers, who to get themſelues a name aboue their neighbours, wil ſeeme to be Gods cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, I commend the wiſe adviſe of <hi>Sirachs</hi> ſonne, c. 3. ver. 22. <hi>Seeke not out the things that are too hard for thee, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſearch the things raſhly, which are too mighty for thee; but what God hath commanded thee, thinke vpon that with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and be not curious in many of his workes; for it is not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15700:5"/> needfull for thee to ſee with thine eies the things that are ſecret.</hi> Such curioſity may further be ſuppreſſed by that of <hi>Elihu,</hi> Iob. 36.26. <hi>Behold, God is excellent, and we know him not:</hi> and by that of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> cap. 32.19. as the vulgar Latine makes him ſpeake, <hi>Incomprehenſibilis cogitatu, our thoughts compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend him not:</hi> and by that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 11.33. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; his waies are paſt finding out.</p>
            <p>Wherefore that we be not <hi>illicitè curioſi, more curious then meete is,</hi> abſteine we from ſearching into ſuch ſecrets as God hath reſerved vnto himſelfe; yet that we be not <hi>damnabiliter ingrati,</hi> as S.<note n="h" place="margin">De vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Gentium lib. 1. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Amhroſe</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>condemned for ingratitude,</hi> let vs vſe our beſt diligence to vnderſtand what God hath revealed of himſelfe. For howſoever <hi>the ſecret things belong to the Lord our God,</hi> yet <hi>the things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed belong vnto vs and our children for ever.</hi> Witneſſe the word of Truth, <hi>Deut. 29.29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is revealed of God, the Father, Sonne, &amp; holy Ghoſt, who is<note n="i" place="margin">Chemnit. Loc. Theol. part. 1. cap. 3. pag 62.</note> 
               <hi>unus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> trinus,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſtyles him, <hi>unus natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ, trinus in perſonis,</hi> a Trinitie in Unitie, and a Unitie in Trinitie; that he is a<note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 10.17</note> God of Gods, and Lord of Lords; a God moſt<note n="l" place="margin">Ecclus. 43.29</note> wonderfull, very<note n="m" place="margin">Deut 10.17</note> great, mighty, &amp; terrible; a God that<note n="n" place="margin">Ecclus. 43.31.</note> cannot be expreſſed by word, nor concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by thought;<note n="o" place="margin">Auguſt. Soli loq. cap. 24.</note> of whom all the Angells in heaven do ſtand in feare, whom all Dominations and Thrones doe adore, at whoſe preſence all powers doe ſhake. A God in <hi>greatneſſe</hi> infinite, in <hi>goodneſſe</hi> Soveraigne, in <hi>wiſdome</hi> wonderfull, in <hi>power</hi> almightie, in <hi>counſels</hi> terrible, in <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> righteous, in <hi>cogitations</hi> ſecret, in <hi>workes</hi> holy, in <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> rich, in <hi>promiſe</hi> true, alway the ſame; eternall, everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, immortall, vnchangeable. Thus haue yee the author of <hi>Davids exaltation.</hi> The <hi>exaltation</hi> it ſelfe followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt ſet him bleſsings for euer.</hi> The Greeke bookes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15700:6"/> haue, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Thou wilt giue him a bleſsing.</hi> So hath S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> ſo hath S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Such ſuperemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lights of the Church cannot want their followers. But I may not forſake the fountaine. The Hebrew words doe thus ſound, <hi>Thou wilt put him,</hi> or, <hi>thou haſt put him</hi> (for the <hi>Enal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage</hi> or interchange of thoſe tenſes is very familiar to that holy tongue) <hi>Thou haſt put him bleſsings. Poſuiſti eum bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictiones.</hi> Supply the Ellipſis of the Prepoſition, and it will be, <hi>Poſuiſti eum in benedictiones.</hi> And whats that?</p>
            <p>Some doe expound it by the contrary, <hi>Poni, Dari, Eſſe in maledictionem,</hi> may be ſaid of one who is become ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,<note place="margin">Moller. in Pſ. 21.</note> and execrable, <hi>ut nomen eius ſerviat imprecationibus, &amp; diris,</hi> as if when you wiſh the extremitie of evill to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you ſhould ſay, God doe to him as hee hath done to ſuch a one. I need not alleage <hi>Homers</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny imprecations of the <hi>Poet</hi> againſt his <hi>Ibis,</hi> for inſtance. <hi>In volumine libri,</hi> in the ſacred volumes we haue an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The phraſe we haue <hi>Ierem. 24.9.</hi> where concerning <hi>Zedechiah,</hi> king of Iudah, and his Princes, thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Dabo eos, I will giue them for a terrible plague to all the kingdomes of the earth, and for a reproch, and for a proverbe, and for a common talke, &amp; in maledictionem, for a curſe. I will giue them for a curſe.</hi> This is explicated, <hi>cap. 29.22.</hi> where thus ſaith the Lord of hoaſts, the God of Iſrael; <hi>They of the captivitie of Iudah that are in Babel, ſhall take vp this curſe, and ſay; The Lord make thee like Zedechiah, and like A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab, whom the king of Babel burnt in the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be the meaning of <hi>Poni, Dari,</hi> or, <hi>Eſſe in maledic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem,</hi> by the law of Contraries we may determine what it is <hi>Poni, Dari,</hi> or, <hi>Eſſe in benedictionem. Poni, Dari, Eſſe in benedictionem,</hi> may be ſaid of one who is ſo happy, ſo proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous,<note place="margin">Moller.</note> 
               <hi>ut ſub nomine eius vota concipiantur,</hi> as if when you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15700:6"/> would wiſh all good to your friend, you ſhould ſay, <hi>ſo God doe to thee as he hath done to ſuch a one.</hi> So did <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſay to <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Gen. 28.4. God all ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bleſſe thee, make thee to encreaſe, multiplie thee, and giue thee the bleſsing of Abraham. God giue thee the bleſsing of Abraham;</hi> as hee bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo bleſſe he thee. According to this expoſition, theſe words, <hi>Poſuiſti eum in benedictiones,</hi> doe carrie this ſenſe, that ſuch was the happy and proſperous eſtate of king David, <hi>ut ſub nomine eius vota concipiantur,</hi> as if praying for our King, we ſhould ſay, <hi>God giue vnto him the bleſsings of David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond expoſition followeth; <hi>Poni, Dari, Eſſe in bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem,</hi> may be ſaid of one, who is full and aboundeth with ſo greate plentie of all good things, that God may ſeeme to haue beene willing to poure out at once all his beneficence vpon him. Turne your eies which way you will, and behold that man, you ſhall ſee nothing but as it were a mirrour of Gods bountie very liberally powred out. To this ſenſe it is ſaid of Chriſt his flocke, <hi>Ezech. 34.26. I will ſet them as a bleſsing eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> round about my mountaine. Pona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eas benedictionem:</hi> the abſtract is put for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>crete. <hi>I will ſet them as a bleſsing,</hi> that is, <hi>I will make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bleſſed. Eſai 39.24.</hi> it is ſaid of Iſrael, that <hi>it ſhall be a bleſsing;</hi>
               <note place="margin">In paraph. in Pſal. 20.</note> and there the Abſtract is for the Concrete. It is <hi>Ianſenius</hi> his obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Iſrael erit benedictio,</hi> id eſt, <hi>erit benedictus,</hi> vel <hi>benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one plenus:</hi> which conſtruction of his well ſorteth with the verſe following, <hi>v. 25.</hi> where it is further added of the ſame Iſrael, <hi>The Lord of hoaſts ſhall bleſſe it, ſaying, Bleſsed be my people.</hi> According to this expoſition, theſe words, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſti eum benedictiones,</hi> doe carrie this ſenſe; God hath ſo appointed <hi>David,</hi> that he may be perpetually bleſſed, both in reſpect of God who endoweth him with immortalitie, and alſo in reſpect of men, of whom hee ſhall for ever bee praiſed.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15700:7"/>
            <p>There is a third expoſition; <hi>Poni, Dari,</hi> or, <hi>Eſſe in benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nem,</hi> may be ſaid of one, who is bleſſed not only in him ſelfe, but is made alſo a bleſſing vnto others, by whome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo are bleſſed, and ſo account themſelues. To this ſenſe God ſaith vnto Abraham <hi>Gen. 12.2. Thou ſhalt bee a bleſsing;</hi> that is, thou ſhalt be not only bleſſed thy ſelfe, but by thee ſhall others alſo be bleſſed: for ſo it followeth, <hi>v. 3 I will bleſſe them that bleſſe thee, and in thee ſhall all families of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> According to this expoſition, thoſe words, <hi>Poſuiſti eum benedictiones,</hi> doe carrie this ſenſe; God tooke David from a poore and meane eſtate, from a ſheepheards life, from <hi>following ewes great with young, Pſal. 78.70.71.</hi> and exalted him to be king over Iſrael, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him in that throne for this ende, that he might be for bleſſings to Iſrael his people. The <hi>ende</hi> then of <hi>Davids ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation,</hi> is <hi>bleſsings</hi> to his people, and it was my third cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt put him bleſsings] Bleſsings,</hi> not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the 70 haue it, nor <hi>Benedictionem</hi> as the vulgar, a <hi>Bleſsing,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>bleſsings,</hi> in the plurall number, to note the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull abundance of Gods graces beſtowed vpon the people through the king. The bleſſings beſtowed vpon Iſraell through <hi>David,</hi> may bee reduced to three heads; one is the worſhip of God reinſtituted in its puritie. 2. Deliverance from forraine enimies. 3. The reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of iudgement and iuſtice. The worſhip of God was reinſtituted in its puritie when David brought the arke of the Lord from the houſe of <hi>Obed-edom</hi> the <hi>Gittite,</hi> into the citie of David, <hi>2. Sam. 6.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The deliverance from forreine enimies was wrought when <hi>David</hi> ſmote <hi>Aram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 8.12.</note> and <hi>Moab,</hi> and <hi>the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and <hi>Edom,</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and <hi>Amalec,</hi> and <hi>Hadade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15700:7"/> the ſonne of <hi>Rehob</hi> king of <hi>Zobah,</hi> and tooke from out their hand <hi>the bridle of bondage, 2, Sam. 8.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That iudgement and iuſtice were reſtored by him, its not obſcurely delivered, <hi>2. Sam. 8.15.</hi> where it is ſaid that <hi>David reigned ouer all Iſraell, and executed iudgment and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to all his people.</hi> In theſe three heads conſiſteth the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a good and godly <hi>King.</hi> Giue ſuch a <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>King</hi> that ſhall promote the worſhip of God according to the word of truth; that ſhall bee victorious over all his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies, that ſhall maintaine his ſubiects through iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and iuſtice, in peace and tranquilitie: Giue ſuch a <hi>king (ſuch a king you enioy)</hi> and he ſhal be a parallel for our David here, and may as well bee ſaid <hi>Poni à Deo in benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiones,</hi> to be placed by God in his throne for this ende, that he may be for bleſſings to vs his people; and that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for ever, which is the <hi>continuance</hi> of the ende, and my laſt circumſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt ſet him bleſsings for ever.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In the Arke of <hi>Noe</hi> it is rendred <hi>aeternitati,</hi> or, <hi>in aeternum;</hi> in the 70 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; in the vulgar Latine, <hi>in ſeculum ſeculi,</hi> for ever. Some take it to ſignifie for a long ſeaſon, as <hi>Pſal. 18.50. Great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances god giveth vnto his king,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wilcox in Pſ. 21.6.</note> 
               <hi>and ſheweth mercy to his annointed, even to David, and to his ſeed for ever. For euer,</hi> that is, faith an expoſitour, for a <hi>long time,</hi> if you refer the words to David and his poſteritie; but if you referre them to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and thoſe that appertaine to him, then it is put for <hi>all eternity.</hi> So here, <hi>Thou haſt ſet him bleſsings for euer:</hi> vnderſtand theſe words to be ſpoken of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and, <hi>For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> is, <hi>For all eternitie:</hi> vnderſtand them to bee ſpoken of <hi>David,</hi> and, <hi>For euer,</hi> is, <hi>For a long ſeaſon.</hi> I haue hitherto expounded theſe words as they are appliable to <hi>David;</hi> and accordingly doe take this laſt word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>For ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15700:8"/>
            <p>David was <hi>à Deo poſitus in benedictiones:</hi> he was ſet for <hi>bleſsings</hi> vnto his people. <hi>Bleſsings temporall</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall: temporall,</hi> as deliverance from forreine enimies, and the execution of iudgement and iuſtice for the peace, &amp; quiet of his people: and <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> as the reeſtabliſhing of the true worſhip of God, whereby his people might become <hi>Citizens of the Saints and of the houſhold of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.19.</note> In reſpect of the former, <hi>For ever,</hi> is for <hi>a long ſeaſon,</hi> for <hi>Davids</hi> life time, which was <hi>Dauids</hi> Ever; <hi>ever,</hi> whileſt he ſwaied the ſcepter of Iſrael. In reſpect of the latter, <hi>For euer,</hi> is for all <hi>eternitie;</hi> for ſpirituall <hi>bleſsings</hi> continue after this life; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> even <hi>for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue I paſt over my foure circumſtances; the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of Davids exaltation, which was <hi>God;</hi> the <hi>exaltation</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>David</hi> placed in the throne of Iſrael; the <hi>ende</hi> of his exaltation, that he might be for bleſſings to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and the <hi>continuance</hi> of this end, <hi>For ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was <hi>God</hi> the author of <hi>Davids exaltation?</hi> Did he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point him to be <hi>king</hi> over Iſrael? Hence then ariſeth this doctrine which before I promiſed to ſpeake vnto, <hi>Kings doe hold their kingdomes immediatly from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A truth ſo vnmoueably grounded vpon the word of truth, that it is ſtrange it ſhould bee controverted. The proofes of ſcripture that do concerne it, are either <hi>generall</hi> or <hi>particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>generall</hi> proofe we haue Rom. 13. In the firſt verſe it is ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The powers that be, are ordained of God.</hi> Therefore the power of a king; of whom it is twiſe ſaide, ver. 5. that he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Gods miniſter; gods lieuetenant, for thy wealth if thou do well; for vengeance, if ill. The like proofe may be taken from Daniel 2.21. where not only the <hi>taking away</hi> of kings, but alſo the <hi>ſetting</hi> of them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15700:8"/> 
               <hi>vp,</hi> is avowed to be gods owne worke. The voice of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome crieth alowd, Prov. <hi>8.15, 16. By me kings raigne, and Princes decree iuſtice; by me Princes rule and the nobles, and all the iudges of the earth.</hi> Theſe proofes were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
            <p>The <hi>particular</hi> do conſiſt in God his immediate deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of diverſe vnto kingdomes. Of <hi>Saul,</hi> 1. Sam. <hi>10.</hi>1. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel tooke a viale of oile, and powred it vpon</hi> Sauls <hi>head, and kiſſed him, and ſaid; Hath not the Lord annointed thee to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour over his inheritance?</hi> Of <hi>Hazael,</hi> and <hi>Iehu,</hi> 1. Kings, <hi>19.15, 16.</hi> The Lord ſaid vnto <hi>Elias; Go annoint Hazael king over Aram, and Iehu the ſonne of Nimſhi ſhalt thou an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint king over Iſrael.</hi> Of <hi>Nabuchodonoſor,</hi> Dan. 2.37. <hi>O king,</hi> ſaith Daniel, <hi>thou art a king of kings; for the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath given thee a kingdome.</hi> Of <hi>Salomon,</hi> 2. Chron. 8.9. The Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> ſaith vnto him, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord thy God which loved thee to ſet thee on his throne as king.</hi> And to omit others, of <hi>David</hi> in my text, of whom it is alſo ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſaid, 1. Chron. 28.4. That <hi>God did chooſe him, and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in him to make him king over Iſrael:</hi> and ver. 3. Pſal. 21. that the Lorde did <hi>ſet a crowne of pure gold vpon his head.</hi> Theſe proofes <hi>generall</hi> or <hi>particular,</hi> ſtanding vpon ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne autoritie, as <hi>Gods word</hi> is of, doe make good my propounded doctrine, namely, <hi>that kings do hold their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes immediatly from God.</hi> Whereto I doubt not but I haue your full aſſent.</p>
            <p>What neede then is there of any further inſiſting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this point? Surely none; were there not a generation of men, bearing in their foreheads the ſtampe of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that cannot brooke any proofe taken out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the maintenance of any doctrine that may diſtaſt the biſhop of Rome, or want his allowance. Tel ſuch that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15700:9"/> by ſcripture it is plaine that <hi>kings hold their kingdomes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God;</hi> their reply wilbe; what tel you vs of <hi>ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi> Set aſide the autority of the <hi>Church,</hi> the autoritie of the <hi>Pope,</hi> &amp; we take ſcripture to be no better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Colloqium Wormat. apud Lubbert. de princip. lib. 1. cap 5.</note> 
               <hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, vncertaine, and leaden rule;</hi> then <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Colloq. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſbon. Rung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu 2.</note> 
               <hi>matter of debate; then a</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Colloq. Wormat. vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>booke of diſcord;</hi> then <hi>a poore</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Hoſius de expreſſo Dei verbo.</note> 
               <hi>kind of element;</hi> then <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pighius co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov. 3. de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia.</note> 
               <hi>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b iudge;</hi> then<note n="x" place="margin">Ludov. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. Lateran.</note> 
               <hi>dead inke;</hi> then<note n="y" place="margin">Eckius.</note> 
               <hi>inken diuinity;</hi> then <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pighius Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erar. l. 3. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>noſe of wax;</hi> then<note n="a" place="margin">Hoſius, Gretſer. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Aeſops fables.</hi> Impious wretches: had they not wiped all ſhame from their faces, they would never haue laid ſuch load of diſgraces vpon Gods holy worde. Their Cardinall <hi>Hoſius</hi> ſtaies not here; he proceedes a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree farther. He coines a diſtinction of ſcripture, <hi>as it is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by themſelues,</hi> whom they call Catholikes, and <hi>as by vs,</hi> whom they call Heretikes. His words are in the end of his third booke againſt <hi>Brentius</hi> his <hi>Prolegomena.</hi> The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>quomodo profertur à Catholicis, verbum eſt Dei; quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do profertur ab haereticis, verbum eſt diaboli:</hi> as it is alleadged by vs, ſo muſt it bee <hi>forſooth</hi> the word of the Devill; but as by them, ſo only ſhall it be the word of God.</p>
            <p>Upon this ground and diſtinction of theirs, I doubt not but that blaſphemous<note n="b" place="margin">Apodix. 1. Theſ. 8. p. 131</note> 
               <hi>Dorhoff,</hi> hath made an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the beginning of our <hi>Creede,</hi> and in ſteede of, <hi>Credo in Deum, patrem omnipotentem, creatorem coeli &amp; terrae,</hi> hath ſubſtituted, <hi>Credo in Diabolum, carnificem, orcipotentem, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptorem coeli &amp; terrae.</hi> For if ſcripture alleaged by vs, be <hi>verbum Diaboli,</hi> what is our beliefe? What our <hi>religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee of what validitie proofes drawne by vs from holy Scriptures for the confutation of any popiſh point, are in the eſtimation of ſome Papiſts. They hold vs for <hi>Heretikes;</hi> and conſequently <hi>the ſenſe of ſcripture</hi> which we bring, to be no <hi>ſenſe of ſcripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence is it that the Author of the ſhort Narration,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15700:9"/> how <hi>Henrie</hi> the IV. (late) king of France and Navarre, ſent his Embaſſadours to Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the VIII. for abſolution from his <hi>hereſie,</hi> tels vs, that though ſome doe mainetaine <hi>the king to hold his kingdome immediately from God,</hi> yet that at Rome this is accounted a very ridiculous matter. It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident to be ſo by <hi>Cardinall Bellarmin,</hi> who in his firſt book <hi>de Romano Pontifice, cap. 7. parag. Poſtremo,</hi> diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>ſecular</hi> and <hi>eccleſiaſticall</hi> ſoveraignty, affirmeth that the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> is <hi>à ſolo Deo, &amp; de iure divino,</hi> from God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and by the law of God; but the <hi>ſecular</hi> is from mans inſtitution, and <hi>de iure gentium,</hi> by the law of nations. If we marke the <hi>antitheſis,</hi> and oppoſition betweene <hi>the lawe of God</hi> &amp; <hi>the law of nations,</hi> as alſo between the ſoveraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> and <hi>ſecular,</hi> we muſt needs acknowledge it for <hi>Bellarmines</hi> opinion, that <hi>kings holde not their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes immediatly from God.</hi> This his opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is more cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet <hi>downe</hi> in his booke <hi>de Clericis, cap. 28. parag. Ad confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationem.</hi> His expreſſe words there are; <hi>Regna non ſunt de iure divino, ſed de iure gentium, &amp; proinde mutabilia ſunt.</hi> Kingdomes are not by Gods law, but by the law of nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and therefore are changeable; wherevpon depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his treaſonable doctrine delivered in his fift booke <hi>de Rom. Pontif. cap. 8.</hi> where among other things, <hi>Parag. Praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> he affirmeth, that not only <hi>Princeps Epiſcoporum,</hi> the Pope, but <hi>Epiſcopus quilibet,</hi> every Biſhop, though but the <hi>Popes</hi> vaſſall, may vſe temporall power over kings; and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them</hi> to make lawes, yea and for ſome cauſes <hi>depoſe</hi> them too, as appeareth by the precedents of that chapter. But this and other like proditorious aſſertions there, and elſewhere broached, and defended by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> &amp; others of that faction vpon this ground, <hi>That kings do not holde their kingdomes immediately from God,</hi> I now let paſſe.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15700:10"/>
            <p>The immediate dependencie of kings, and their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes vpon God (howſoever at Rome it be ridiculouſly entertained) hath already bin prooved, and warranted ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently to ſuch as do beleeue the ſcriptures. Unbeleevers I much heede not. Yet if any will that the autority of the ancient fathers be produced, let ſuch know that<note n="a" place="margin">Ad utilitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gentiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renum regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſitum eſt à Deo, ſed non à diabolo, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in his 5. booke <hi>aduerſus haereſes,</hi> &amp;<note n="b" place="margin">Chriſtianus nulliꝰ eſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis, nedu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratoris; quem ſcien à Deo ſuo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitui, neceſſe eſt ut &amp; ipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diligat &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercatur, &amp; honoret, &amp; ſalvum velit cum toto Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano Impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rio quouſque ſeculum ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.— Colimꝰ ergo &amp; Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem ſic, quomodo &amp; nobis licet &amp; ipſi expedit, ut hominem à Deo ſecundum, &amp; quicquid eſt, à Deo conſecutum, &amp; ſolo Deo minorem. Hoc &amp; ipſe volet. Sic enim omnibus major eſt, dum ſolo vero deo minor eſt. Et Apologet. cont. gent. cap. 30. Sciunt [Imperatores] quis illia dederit imperium, ſciunt quà homines, quis &amp; animam. Sentiunt enim Deum eſſe ſolum, in cujus ſolius poteſtate ſunt, à quo ſunt ſecundi, poſt quem primi, ante omnes &amp; ſuper omnes deos. Quid-ni? Cum ſuper omnes homines qui ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vivunt, &amp; mortuis antiſtant.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> in the <hi>2. cap.</hi> of his booke to <hi>Scapula,</hi> &amp;<note n="c" place="margin">Super Imperatorem non [eſt] niſi ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Deus qui fecit Imperatorem.</note> 
               <hi>Optatus</hi> in his 3. booke againſt <hi>Parmenian,</hi> and <hi>S.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Laeſus eſt [Imperator] qui non habet parem ullum ſuper terram, ſummitas &amp; caput omnium ſuper terram hominum.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in <hi>2. Hom. ad Pop. Antioch.</hi> and <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> in his<note n="e" place="margin">Cap. 4. Qui tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur legibus, audent ſuum negare peccatum, dedignantur rogare indulgentiam, quam pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebat [Rex David] qui nullis legibus tenebatur humanis. &amp; ibid. cap. 10. Rex utique erat, nullis ipſe legibus tenebatur, quia liberi ſunt reges à vinculis delictorum. Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ad poenam vocantur legibus tuti imperij poteſtate. Homini ergo non peccavit cui non tenebatur obnoxius.</note> 
               <hi>Apolo.</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>S.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Deus igitur ille faelicitatis autor &amp; dator, quia ſolus eſt verus Deus; ipſe dat regna terrena &amp; bonis &amp; malis, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 4. booke <hi>de Civ. D. cap. 33.</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Lib. 2. cap. 100. indict. 11. <hi>Mauritio Auguſto;</hi> Ego verò haec Dominis meis loquens, quid ſum niſi pulvis &amp; vermis. Sed tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quia contra autorem omnium Deum hanc intendere conſtitutionem ſentio, Dominis ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere non poſſum. Ad hoc enim poteſtas ſuper omnes homines Dominorum meorum pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati coelitus data eſt, ut qui bona appetunt adjuventur, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Gregorie the firſt</hi> in an epiſtle of his to <hi>Mauritius the</hi> Emperour, do all ſtand very effectually for the imperiall authority of kings <hi>immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly derived from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How this point hath beene mainetained for theſe laſt 500 yeares by <hi>Venericus Vercellenſis</hi> in his booke <hi>de unitate Eccleſiae conſervanda;</hi> by the <hi>Leodienſes</hi> in their epiſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Paſchalis</hi> the ſecond; by <hi>Parrhiſius</hi> in his treatiſe <hi>de
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15700:10"/> poteſtate regiâ &amp; papali;</hi> by <hi>Babenbergius,</hi> by <hi>Dantes,</hi> by <hi>Cuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> by <hi>Theodoricus de Niem,</hi> by <hi>Franciſcus de Zabarellis,</hi> and others, they, who haue pervſed that profitable volume ſet out by <hi>Simon Schardius</hi> concerning <hi>Imperiall</hi> Iuriſdiction, authority, and praeeminence, cannot but ſee. And how it is in this our age vpholden againſt all gaineſayers, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here a line and there a line, but booke vpon booke pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by the now-Mirrour of kings, by our Biſhops, &amp; by others (eminent for their learning) as well within this land, as without, ſhall make it well knowne to the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are yet vnborne: who in their day (moved by the ſame evidence of Gods word, whereby wee are moved) ſhall ioine their aſſent to ours, &amp; teach their children alſo, that <hi>Kings doe hold their kingdomes immediately from God.</hi> You haue my doctrine.</p>
            <p>It may ſerue to check that man of ſinne who intrudes himſelfe into Gods right, and takes vpon him the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigntie over all kings and people; and claimes abſolute and vncontroleable autoritie, to giue &amp; to take away <hi>(im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peria, regna, principatus, &amp; quicquid habere mortales poſſunt)</hi> to giue and to take away empires, kingdomes, principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and whatſoever mortall men can poſſeſſe or haue. This was the expreſſe challenge of <hi>Pope Gregory</hi> the 7. in his execration againſt the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. as it is ſet downe by <hi>Platina</hi> in that Popes life. Were his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours leſſe arrogant? I ſuppoſe not. See but the Bull of <hi>Pope Alexander</hi> the <hi>Sixt,</hi> containing his donation of the weſt Indies to Ferdinandus king of Caſtell and Leon, and to Iſabella his Queene: we <hi>de noſtra mera liberalitate,</hi> of our meere liberalitie, and of the fulneſſe of our Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call power, doe giue vnto you, your heires, &amp; ſucceſſours, <hi>kings of Caſtell, and Leon</hi> for ever, all <hi>Ilands</hi> and <hi>firme lands</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15700:11"/> detected or to be detected from one hundred leagues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>Acores</hi> towards the weſt and ſouth, togither with all their <hi>dominions, citties, caſtles, places, farmes, rightes, iuriſdictions, appurtenances</hi> whatſoever. This was a largeſſe ſo tranſcendent for the vanitie thereof, that (as<note n="c" place="margin">Hiſt. Nov. orb. l. 3. c. 3. p. 281.</note> 
               <hi>Benzo</hi> writeth) an infidell king <hi>Attabaliba,</hi> king of <hi>Peru</hi> could by the eie of reaſon diſcover it, and giue it this cenſure, <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificem inſigniter fatuum, &amp; impudentem eſse, eo facilè prodi, quòd aliena tam liberalit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r largiatur:</hi> that the Pope was paſſing fooliſh &amp; impudent, ſo liberally to giue that which was none of his owne. A like vanitie did <hi>Sanctius</hi> brother to the king of Spaine, and elect Generall for the warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Saracens of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> taxe in another Biſhop of Rome, as<note n="d" place="margin">De rob. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morand. lib. 2 tract. 3. c. 22.</note> Petrarch affirmeth. The biſhop of Rome cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to be proclaimed in his conſiſtory; that hee beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the kingdome of Aegypt vpon <hi>Sanctius. Sanctius</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by his interpreter this favour, for requitall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that the Pope ſhould by and by bee proclaimed <hi>Great Caliph of Baldach.</hi> So perfumed he the ſonne of pride with his owne ſmoke; for he knew full well that the Pope could no more make him a King, then he could the Pope a <hi>Caliph.</hi> But <hi>Popes,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Divines,</hi> and <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> and all <hi>Clawbackes</hi> of that See, maintaining that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>iure divino,</hi> by the law of God, ſo large and faire a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie, as is the Monarchie, and Soveraigntie over the whole world, in all cauſes, both <hi>Civill</hi> &amp; <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> they all ſtand convicted of <hi>falſhood</hi> through the <hi>truth</hi> of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred doctrine; <hi>Kings doe hold their kingdomes immediately from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Immediately from God?</hi> Let then the honour be Gods; and let our hearts be powred out to giue due thankes to him for placing over vs our Gratious King, <hi>King</hi> IAMES:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15700:11"/> of whom we may as truely ſay as the Iſraelites did of their David, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Thou haſt ſet him bleſsings for ever.</hi> Aged <hi>Leontius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> (as it is recorded by <hi>Sozomen Eccleſ. hiſt. lib. 3. c.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In verſione Chriſtophor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoni, &amp; Gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naei, cap. 19.</note> 
               <hi>20.</hi>) pointing to his gray and white haires, ſaid vnto ſome that were preſent with him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>when this ſnow is melted, much mire will follow:</hi> he meant <hi>ſedition</hi> and <hi>trouble.</hi> But God hath done better by vs. The white ſnowie haires of our late aged Soveraigne were in her full time diſſolved. But God his wonderfull providence, contrarie to the deſires and expectation of many, ſo ordered matters then, that no trouble followed. The Lord left vs not as ſheep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſheepheard.<note n="e" place="margin">Numantius ad Scipione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apud Plutarc. Apophtheg. Rom.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; we are the ſame ſheep ſtill to be lead forth to the waters of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, though there be another ſheepheard. The Lord did ſet <hi>King</hi> IAMES to be vnto vs <hi>bleſsings for ever: bleſsings temporall</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall. Temporall;</hi> for through him wee are delivered from all feare of forraine enimies, &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and iuſtice are executed to vs for the quiet of vs all. And <hi>ſpirituall;</hi> for the worſhip of God is every where within his dominions promoted according to the word of truth. And this bleſſing is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for ever:</hi> for hereby are we fitted to that eternall inheritance in the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens. I will not now make a panegyricke to extoll his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie for his <hi>Clemencie, Equitie, Bountie, Pietie, Learning, Theory,</hi> and other kingly parts: the time forbids me, and bids me to conclude. My concluſion ſhall be no other, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a prayer for his Maieſtie, that God would be pleaſed to giue him <hi>vitam longam, regnum proſperum, prolem foelicem, vitam aeternam,</hi> a long life, a proſperous raigne, a happy progeny in this world, and in the world to come life eternall.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15700:12"/>
            <p>Holy Lord, ſtabliſh the good worke, that thou haſt wrought in him: viſite him as thou diddeſt <hi>Moſes</hi> in the buſh, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in the battell, <hi>Gedeon</hi> in the field, <hi>Samuel</hi> in the temple. Be thou vnto him in his counſell wiſdome, and in all his waies his <hi>rocke,</hi> his <hi>fortreſſe,</hi> his <hi>deliverer,</hi> his <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>strength,</hi> that the hand of violence, of rebellion, of treaſon touch him not. So ſhall we vnder his governement lead a quiet, and a peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſtie: wherein whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal haue finiſhed our race with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we looke to be delivered from this bondage of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the glorious libertie of the ſonnes of God; at what time our vile bodies ſhall be changed, &amp; ſhalbe faſhioned like vnto the glorious body of our Lord &amp; Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Even ſo bee it bleſſed Father, for the ſame Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to whom with thee in the vnitie of the holy Spirit be aſcribed all praiſe and power, might &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, dignitie, and dominion for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15700:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
